<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the assizes at Norwich upon the fifth day of August, 1693 by J.R., M.A., Rector of Brundal.</title>
            <author>Russell, John, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57933</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2344</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5459</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12580721</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12580721</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63738</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57933)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63738)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 331:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the assizes at Norwich upon the fifth day of August, 1693 by J.R., M.A., Rector of Brundal.</title>
                  <author>Russell, John, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Hayes ... for Samuel Oliver ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Russell. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [1] at beginning and on p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Mark XXII, 17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:63738:1"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THERE is publiſhed by the ſame Author, a ſmall Treatiſe, entitituled, <hi>Religion the Perfection of Man:</hi> In 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63738:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the ASSIZES AT NORWICH, Upon the Fifth Day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1693.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. R.</hi> M. A. Rector of <hi>Brundal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>CAMBRIDGE,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Hayes,</hi> Printer to the Univerſity, For <hi>Samuel Oliver,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Norwich.</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:63738:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>January</hi> 12. 1693/4.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Guil. Stanley,</hi> Procan.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Beaumont,</hi> S. Th. Pr.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Eachard,</hi> Aul. Cath. Magiſter.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ja. Balderſon,</hi> Coll. Emman. Magiſter.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63738:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Mark 12.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—Render to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and to God the things that are Gods.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eligion and Government being the two great Inſtitutions that Nature dictates, and that God hath ordained for the Benefit of Mankind; The one for our preſent tranquillity, and to give us the Advantage of Society, and peace in the world; And the other for ſecuring of our Greater Intereſts both here and hereafter, Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the diſorders and inconveniencies our diſcompoſed Nature and ruffled State hath ſubjected us to, and involved us in; The Wiſdom of God, and the Saviour of men, abundantly demonſtrating his love to the World, hath both improved Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to the utmoſt Capacity of Aſſiſting its Great Deſign, and taken all poſſible Care to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh Government: He hath ſupported the Authority and ſtrengthened the Neceſſity of both by his Laws; and that men may obtain the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py end of both, he hath moſt indiſpenſably en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd that they <hi>Render to Caeſar the things that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63738:3"/>are Caeſars, and to God the things that are Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sometimes indeed the Deſign of Religion is fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated; The Errours and Corruptions that ſome mix with it, diſappointing them of the Salvation they are in purſuit of; And ſometimes alſo the deſign of Government is ſo perverted, that men have not that benefit of Security and Peace under it, that God and Nature ſeem to have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended them thereby; That as it is a matter of Great Difficulty, in ſome Churches eſpecially, to obtain <hi>the end of our faith;</hi> ſo in ſome States it is really as difficult, <hi>to lead quiet and peaceable lives:</hi> Nevertheleſs, the foundation of God ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſure, and when the face of the World is moſt uneven, and the times moſt Critical, when Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and Confuſion are moſt rampant in the World, to pay a due obſervance to Princes, and to obſerve a due regard to God, is to reſerve our Peace in both Worlds, as ſafe as any Rules can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, or practice effect.</p>
            <p>To pretend ſo much conſcience toward God, as to deny a due Honour to Princes, if it be not a mere Sham and the Covert of ill Deſign, yet ſeems an errour in practice, being moſt evidently a lameing of the Good Deſign which the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God hath contrived for our Peace, and a forward ſtep to thoſe troubles that are commonly awarded to ſuch as are ſtubborn and diſobedient: And on the other ſide, to reſolve all Religion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Loyalty, is as ridiculous and abſurd, as to ſay the <hi>Roman</hi> is the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> and may prove of as ill Conſequence and worſe: But as pure Religion eſtabliſhed and faithfully practiſed, and Government well ſettled and Prudently ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63738:3"/>is the moſt Natural and Rational ground for the Repoſe of the World, ſo thoſe men that concur therewith, and bearing a due regard to both, with upright minds <hi>Render to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and to God the things that are Gods,</hi> not only conſult well for the Glory of God, and the Publick. Tranquillity, but alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate themſelves <hi>good Subjects, good Chriſtians, and Wiſe Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe I am ſure our Lord would have us to be, and I fuppoſe his words in the Text drive at it, and therefore I ſhall endeavour in this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to aſſiſt his Deſign; And to this end I ſhall obſerve to you, that there is in the Words;</p>
            <p>Firſt, Something granted, <hi>viz.</hi> That there is a Due or Right that belongs to the Prince, and to God, which ought to be rendred to them;</p>
            <p>Secondly, That there is ſomething ſuppoſed, <hi>viz.</hi> That theſe Rights are conſiſtent with one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and that men may <hi>render to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars,</hi> and yet <hi>render to God the things that are Gods,</hi> or that men may be good Subjects with ſafe Conſciences.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, There is ſomething enjoyned, <hi>viz.</hi> That we render to each his Due.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, There is ſomething intimated, <hi>viz.</hi> That as there is ſometimes Great Prudence required in this Practice, ſo there is Great Security in it: In rendring <hi>to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and to God the things that are Gods,</hi> there is Wiſdom and Safety.</p>
            <p>All theſe I ſhall diſcourſe a little upon, and I hope they will give me the Advantage of making
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63738:4"/>ſome Good Improvement, for the Glory of God, the Repoſe of the World, and the Good of Men both here and hereafter.</p>
            <p>Firſt, There is in the Text ſomething granted, which is that there is a Due or Right belonging to the Prince, and to God, that ought to be rendred.</p>
            <p>This is indeed the Foundation of all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Government, without which all kind of Confuſion, Impiety, and Idolatry would enſue, that the diſordered State of Mankind is ſubject to: And it is ſo Natural, as well as Chriſtian a Maxime, that it hath the Univerſal aſſent of all Nations and Ages. Neither hath it been thought any infringing either of Liberty or Property, if rightly underſtood; for as the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>we are not our own,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.19.</note> that is, ſo abſolutely, as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all others from any Intereſt in us, ſo all that we have is not to be accounted ſo entirely ours, that none elſe can claim a Right to any part of it but our ſelves: We do not ſubſiſt of our ſelves, but do indeed entirely depend upon God, and all that we have and are, is from him; he hath a Right to us and in us; and what we have, we hold from him, and conſequently an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement at leaſt is more his due, then the remainder ours. We hold what we have by the Power of Government, and it is the Prince that defends our Perſons, and that maintains us in the poſſeſſion of what God beſtows upon us; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently an acknowledgement and aſſiſtance is due to him; ſo that there are three Parties that are concern'd and intereſted both in our Perſons and Poſſeſſions, <hi>viz.</hi> God, the Prince, and our
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63738:4"/>ſelves: God hath a Right, the Prince a Right, and the reſidue is Property; And what is reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to them, is, if paid, as a Quit-rent which enſures and confirms the reſt to us; And if we be obliged to render it, it is not to be accounted an infringing of our Liberty, becauſe it is the moſt Rational way, to ſecure both it and our ſelves.</p>
            <p>That there is a Due to be rendred to the Prince; not only the neceſſity of Government re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, but it ſeems to be his intermixt Right with his Subjects, in them and their Poſſeſſions, that denominates him Lord, and is the ground of Dominion and Rule; in as much as without ſuch a Right there could be no claim to either, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Power of Government cannot be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained without it. That every one ſhould be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute in his own Poſſeſſions, and all level Lords of their own Fee, is rather a hoped Chimera of diſtempered heads, then a poſſible attainment of the wiſeſt Men; for if all were abſolute Lords, and had not a common Head to unite themſelves under into a Body, againſt the Deſigns and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of any that are Covetous-and Ambitious, and withall Active and Daring, there would be continual bickering and Conteſts, till a forced ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion be gained to a Conquering Tyrant that would have all: But the uniting of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity into Society, prevents confuſion, and the individuals conceding to the Supremacy of one, and his being intereſted in them, as they in him, is the method,<note place="margin">Prov. 8.15.</note> which the <hi>Divine Wiſdom</hi> care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the Concerns of Mankind, hath eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon a Natural neceſſity for their Good: This ſeems to be the Foundation of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63738:5"/>which is of ſuch a Nature, that there is neceſſarily a Due to be rendred to him that orders and manageth it.</p>
            <p>But then the Queſtion will be, how comes this to be any one mans Right and not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? <hi>Caeſar</hi> hath a Right, but who hath the Right to be <hi>Caeſar?</hi> To which the words of <hi>Daniel,</hi> or rather of that voice that came from Heaven, may be given in anſwer, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.25, 32. <hi>The moſt high ruleth in the kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomſoever he will.</hi> As Government is <hi>the Ordinance of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.2.</note> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of natural neceſſity for the good of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, ſo the Great Lord of the World, <hi>the King of kings, and the Lord of lords,</hi> as he hath the Right, ſo he doth put in his own Deputies, and that not always according to the common Methods of aſcending to Empire and Rule, but as on purpoſe to aſſert and demonſtrate his own Prerogative: For th<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Obſervation and Event have taught us that the uſual way is either by Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, Election, or Conqueſt, yet ſometimes Princes arrive at their Dignities, in a way that cannot well be reduced to any of thoſe Rules; And therefore <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſpeaks of a fourth way which he calls <hi>Dono Superioris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellarm.</hi> de Contrev. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> whereby he does not mean <hi>by Donation from the Pope,</hi> (thô it be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable enough with his thoughts) but <hi>ſpeciali dono Dei, by the ſpecial gift of God.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath the ſole Right to ſet up and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point whom he will, thoſe that he inveſts with the Government, (whether by the common Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, or by ſome ſpecial and ſingular Providence,) have a Right to that Due by the juſteſt and moſt Venerable Title in the World.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:63738:5"/>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> who were the People concerned in the Text, had anciently a Charter from Heaven that entail'd the Crown upon the houſe of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> ſo that there was in that Family a <hi>Divine Right</hi> to it and its appurtenances; And it ſeems that according thereto <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth</hi> was <hi>the king of the Jews,</hi> thô the aforeſaid Cardinal would deprive him of that Hereditary Right, as being deſcended of <hi>Jechonias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellarm.</hi> ſuprat Ad quid illud jus, quo nunquam uſuri erant.</note> and would not have him be accounted King <hi>de jure,</hi> becauſe he was not to be ſo <hi>de facto:</hi> But for once we will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that the <hi>Roman Procurator</hi> was more in the Right, than the <hi>Cardinal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 19.19.</note> and that <hi>Jeſus of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth was the king of the Jews;</hi> And yet ſince the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour was inveſted with that Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, in complyance with the order of Heaven he ſuperſeded his own Right, and declared for him that was in Poſſeſſion; And thô the Princes of this World will not alway ſo exactly follow his Example, yet his Doctrine ought to take place; and for as much as he requires that <hi>Auguſtus</hi> ſhould have <hi>Caeſars</hi> due, we may rationally inferr and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that he that is inveſted with the Sovereignty hath a Right to that due which is here granted in the Text.</p>
            <p>What and how much that Due is the words do not define, neither will I preſume to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine; only thus much the Nature of the thing ſeems to exact, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Right or Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to Govern is the Princes due, as it is his Prerogative; And conſequently, ſuch Honour is due to the Head, and ſuch Submiſſion and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, as is neceſſary to conſtitute Government, and to anſwer the Deſign of Heaven in appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63738:6"/>it: As for Tribute and Taxes they are but that ſhare which the Prince hath in the Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his Subjects, for the Defence and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Government; and thô there are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly very preſſing Reaſons for thoſe Humane Laws that exact them; the Divine Precepts for giving <hi>tribute to whom tribute,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.6, 7</note> and <hi>cuſtom to whom cuſtom</hi> is due, thô founded upon the moſt ſolid Reaſon, Equity, and Wiſdom, need nothing more to render them obliging, than the Will of him who is the Supreme Lord and Monarch of the World. The ſervice alſo of the Perſons of his Subjects for the Defence of his Perſon, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and Government, ſeems to be a due that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily belongs to the Prince, becauſe he alone cannot be ſuppoſed able to do it: As for Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude as well as Honour, it is ever due to him that bears the burden for us, and Love and Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs are always the Merit of Gracious and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent Princes. What other Dues there are, the Conſtitutions and Cuſtoms of Kingdoms and States will beſt direct: For thô Society and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently Government ſtands upon a Natural ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, and is the Order of Heaven, yet there ſeems to be no Particular Rules for the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of States ſet down in Gods word, (ſince the Jewiſh Oeconomy was diſſolved:) But the Prudence of Men in all Regular States, invents Laws agreeable to the Genius of People, and the Scituation and Climate of Countreys, that may beſt conduce to their Welfare; And where there is a Regular Aſcenſion to Principality, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſtipulate with their People, and enter upon the Government according to the Rules of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63738:6"/>State, the received Laws are at once the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and the Princes Guide, and determine his Due and their Duty.</p>
            <p>And as it is granted in the Text, that there is a Due belonging to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> ſo alſo is it, that there is a Due to <hi>God:</hi> For thô for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of Mankind and the Peace of the World, he hath imparted of his Power and Authority to Princes for the Government of Men, yet he hath not ſo deveſted himſelf, as only to retain the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty name of <hi>King of kings, and Lord of lords.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 19.16.</note> It is ſo far from this, that Princes themſelves in their Higheſt Orbs are but his ſervants; <hi>the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God,</hi> for the Adminiſtration of the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the World: And thô as his Vicegerents upon Earth they are Highly Exalted above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yet they in common with the meaneſt of the People, muſt account for their Faith and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to the Author of their Beings, and give an account of their Stewardſhip before the Great Judge at the laſt day. And ſo much doth he reſerve this his Right and Sovereignty over all his Creatures, that he will be Owned and Adored for ever, as <hi>the bleſſed and only Potentate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.15.</note> in whom the Devotion and Service of Heaven and Earth, of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Men muſt center.</p>
            <p>It is not therefore proper to ask of how great extent Gods Right is, ſince it comprehends all; the eaſier way to know our Duty is to enquire what conceſſions he hath made to Men; and what is not granted, is yet reſerved as his own Right. To Princes he hath granted Authority, and a Right to Rule, and ſuch an Intereſt both in the Perſons and Poſſeſſions of their Subjects
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63738:7"/>as is neceſſary to Conſtitute Government, and Maintain Order and Peace: To Men in General he hath given <hi>the earth with the fulneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of;</hi> And Juſtice managed by the hand of the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, is to determine what by the Merit and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement of Humane Induſtry, or by the Divine diſpoſings, is every particular Mans Right. As for our ſelves, <hi>We are not our own,</hi> but are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved as the peculiar Poſſeſſion of our Creator and our Lord, and all that we muſt pretend to, is that we are his ſervants: yet ſome are more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly reſerved for Gods more immediate ſervice, as the <hi>Levites</hi> among the <hi>Jews;</hi> and now the Miniſters of the Goſpel are Gods (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, his Portion conſecrated to him out of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Stock; and it ſeems not only Expedient, but Neceſſary and Juſt that there ſhould be a continual Stock conſecrated to God for the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement and Tranſaction of Religious Matters and Divine Worſhip, as well as Rules for the Adminiſtration of Secular Affairs in the World. As for our Poſſeſſions, he that <hi>gives us all things richly to enjoy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.17.</note> yet reſerves a part for an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement, that what we have, we hold from him: Sacrifices therefore and Oblations were from the beginning Rites or Modes of agnizing him Lord of the Creatures, and our Benefactor, and conſequently to be duely and devoutly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered and paid; The Maintenance alſo of Gods <hi>Clergy,</hi> and of his Worſhip, was ever a Divine Right and Reſervation, which Nature taught the Heathen,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.14.</note> and the Goſpel teacheth Chriſtians: And above all things, the Love and Devotion of our Souls, with all kind of Religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63738:7"/>is ſo much Gods peculiar Right, that no Creature muſt preſume to claim it to himſelf, to confer it upon any thing elſe, or deny it him: And whatever other dues there are, Gods word, which is our Beſt Counſellour, will direct, and a well informed Conſcience is our beſt Guide. Thus, as it is granted in the Text, there is a Due be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to God, as there is alſo to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> which ought to be rendred.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is ſuppoſed in the words, that theſe are conſiſtent, and that Men may render to each his Due without infringing the others Right, and may be Good Subjects with a ſafe Conſcience. For that Wiſdom of God, <hi>by whom Kings reign,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.33.</note> is in no wiſe <hi>the Author of Confuſion;</hi> but as in the great Machin of the World, the Almighty hand of the Wiſe Creator hath placed a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of vaſt Orbs which continually obſerve their ſeveral Motions without interfering with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: or as in Political States, there are divers Societies and Corporations, neither juſtling with one another, nor yet with the State it ſelf, but obſerving their order in their proper Sphere, are rather an Aſſiſtance to the Publick, than a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance to it; ſo in the Regiment of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, that part of it which the Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath committed to Men, is like the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets <hi>wheel within a wheel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bzek. 10.10</note> moving upon the ſame Axis with the Divine Providence General, and ſerves as a means to carry on its diſpoſings about Humane Affairs. It cannot be ſuppoſed that God Inſtituted a check to his own Authority, when he granted Sovereignty to Princes, nor delegated his Power to diſturb the Wiſe and Benign De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63738:8"/>of his Counſel, but rather on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that as Princes are his Miniſters, they are to preſerve the Divine Rights and as they are the Governours or Rulers of Men, they are to concur with, and aſſiſt the Gracious Deſigns of his Providence towards the World; to keep Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Peace in it; to divide between Man and Man the Bounty that Heaven beſtows upon them, and then to Maintain them in it againſt Aggreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; to preſerve their Subjects, and to do their Country Good; to defend the Innocent, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Righteous, and to puniſh the Wrong Doers; And that they may be able to do all this (as in Duty to God they are bound) to preſerve the Authority that Heaven hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them, leſt they be able to do none at all: Such we muſt conceive the Natural Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Government according to the Divine Inſtitution and Intention, and conſequently that <hi>Caeſars</hi> Due and Gods are ſo far from being incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent, that they mutually Aſſiſt and Support one another; God gives Authority to Princes, and that Authority ſerves as a means to carry on his kind Intentions to the World. So that the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is not ſo much whether a Man may be a Good Subject with a ſafe Conſcience, as whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Man can be a Good Chriſtian, that is not ſo? or whether a Man can <hi>render to God the things that are Gods,</hi> and not <hi>render to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars?</hi> For Government is the Inſtitution of Nature and <hi>the Ordinance of God,</hi> Princes are his Vicegerents, and their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to bleſs the World with Tranquillity and Peace; ſo that not to <hi>render to Caeſar the things
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63738:8"/>that are Caeſars,</hi> ſeems to affront the Great Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour and Judge of the World, to be injurious to the Publick, and to offer our Talent to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce all thoſe Evils that our diſcompoſed State is ſubject to, and which the kind Intentions of Heaven deſign to prevent: Onely there is this in the way; Things do not always anſwer their ends, and the Good Intentions of God and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are at once fruſtrated and abuſed: Through Pride and Ambition ſome Princes, inſtead of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, have themſelves Invaded the Divine Rights, exacting Divine Honour to their Perſons, and a ſubjection of their Subjects Conſciences to their Will; and others taking the Advantage of their Power, inſtead of thoſe kind Offices that God hath given them in charge, Tyrannize over their People, demanding of them what was never grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them: ſo that the caſe is, who ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide between God and the King, and between him and his Subjects? For it ſeems too forward a ſtep to Slavery and Idolatry <hi>to obey without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation and reſerve.</hi> But as thoſe are the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieſt States that are Governed by fixed Laws, and not by the Arbitrary Power of Princes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe Laws are ſtanding Rules, and ſecure the Subject againſt any Invaſion either of his Liberty or Property, eſpecially when unbyaſſed and Righteous Judges interpret and execute them; ſo the Laws of God, and the received Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Divine Inſtruction will beſt decide the caſe between God and the Prince, which, if Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces will not obſerve in their Demands, Subjects muſt in their Obedience, becauſe they are to be judged thereby at laſt: and therefore theſe are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63738:9"/>always better Counſellours than our own Puſilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity or Secular Intereſt, or the obſequiouſneſs of others; and a better Guide than the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing humour of Paraſites or the Practice of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious and Devoted Courtiers, as was well ſeen in the caſe of <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>three children.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 3.26, 27, 30. Chap. 6.22, 28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In ſuch Difficult Caſes as theſe, there is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed need of <hi>the wiſdom of the ſerpent, and the innocence of doves,</hi> and the Reſolution of Men. But when Princes demands, are at once congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and ſubſervient to the Will of God, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of Government, and the Common Good of Men, all Difficulties and Cavils are ſuperſeded, and there is no hinderance in the caſe, (except it be Diſhoneſty and Ill Deſign,) but that a Man may <hi>render to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and to God the things that are Gods;</hi> Here is no ſnare, but onely a ground laid for the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, the Repoſe of the World, and the Security of Men both here and hereafter: Onely this muſt be obſerved, that ſince the thing is poſſible and practicable, it muſt be done.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This is that which is enjoyned in the Text; and it is the doing of our Duty that chiefly recommends us both to God and Man: Thoſe Men that fail in theſe Practicks, are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Good Subjects, Good Chriſtians, nor (in this caſe) Wiſe Men; but they that do them, ſo far at leaſt, are all: they therefore that own them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves either Chriſtians or Subjects, or that intend to act Wiſely for themſelves, ſhall do well to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this Injunction of our Saviour, which ought to be more Obliging than all the Intereſts in the World, becauſe it is his.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:63738:9"/>
            <p>To talk of Good Things, and diſcourſe of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and cenſure others, hath been the chief part of the Religion of ſome; and by this means they have gained the Reputation of Good People, whilſt they have deceived the World and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; And to ſpeak high <hi>for Kings and thoſe in Authority,</hi> hath been the Chief Part of the Loyalty of others, whilſt they Betrayed the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers they Adored, buoying up Authority to demands that were moſt likely to ruine either it, or them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; But when a juſt and neceſſary Submiſſion is required, in complyance with what Heaven hath Ordained, and Nature it ſelf demands for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Safety, it is denied. But both theſe ſeem to fall ſhort of the Character of Wiſe and Good Men; for as Virtue chiefly conſiſts in Practice, ſo doth Wiſdom, and therefore they that would at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain both, muſt do their Duty: And doubtleſs a little conſideration will teach us that an <hi>honeſt ſimplicity and Godly ſincerity</hi> in all things is the Beſt Policy, and eſpecially in the preſent caſe, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt Rational way to reſerve our Peace in both Worlds.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, And this is that which our Saviour ſo plainly intimates to us in the Text; <hi>viz.</hi> That in rendring <hi>to Caeſar the things that are Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars, and to God the things that are Gods,</hi> there is Wiſdom and Safety. He knew that Malice it ſelf could not lay hold of ſuch Integrity, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly they that came to entangle him in his talk, <hi>marvelled and left him, and went away:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 22.12.</note> And it ſeems alſo, that thô they deſigned to bring him in danger of the State, yet in his wonted tenderneſs and Clemency, he gives them a Rule,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63738:10"/>at the ſame time he anſwered for himſelf, that might be as effectual to ſecure them, as he knew it would himſelf; For he certainly foreſaw That Peoples ruine, and their untractableneſs to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment they were under, would bring that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction upon them, which by their repeated and continued Impieties they had prepared for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: And they might as well have obſerved the <hi>innuendo</hi> in his Anſwer, as they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of its Wiſdom; And had they taken the hint, and acted accordingly, they would have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced it a moſt certain Method for their ſafety; ſo that indeed we have not onely a ſure Rule for Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Safety, but a Topick of Divine Policy for that of the Publick.</p>
            <p>For firſt, Government being the onely Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Method for the Preſervation of Society, and giving Men all the Advantage that can be of Tranquillity and Security in the World, the onely Rational way to eſtabliſh it, and render it capable of anſwering its ends, is to be juſt to him that manageth it, and render him what may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able him to preſerve both it and them; whereas on the contrary, he that detracts his ſhare for the Preſervation and Defence of the Government he lives under (eſpecially if it be well ordered and directed to the Proper Ends for which it is Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained) ſeems to act the part of one that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſes to lend his hand to Defend the Banks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Sea, or to ſtop a Raging Fire in his Neighbourhood, and conſequently deſerves to be treated as one of the Greateſt Nuiſances in the Common wealth: And indeed every well order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed State is obliged to juſtifie its ſelf againſt ſuch
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63738:10"/>as deny it thoſe juſt Dues that are neceſſary for its Support, and to exact at leaſt the Penalty of thoſe Laws that are provided for its Defence and Peace. And thô ſome are ſo mild and tender as not to take the Advantage of Mens errors, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing that even all ſhould have the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of Peace and Security, yet it ſeems neceſſary to take Notice of continued Obſtinacy, leſt ill Men ſhould think the Government too weak to Vindicate its ſelf, and ſo be incouraged to attempt its Ruine. And if any think to eſcape the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Law by ſuch attempts, yet the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions they create, may chance to affect them ſo, as to make them Repent of their Indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; For as it belongs to God alone to make Alterations in the World, ſo he onely is able in Great Revolutions to make all things fall Right: but when the Folly and Diſtempers of Men ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite them to break in pieces that Order of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that it hath demonſtrated, and they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience to be full of Grace, as they will be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to make all things jump with their Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations, (for that muſt be left to God at laſt) ſo in all likelyhood, they will taſte the reſentments of contemned Goodneſs, and be overwhelmed in the Deluge they let in; And for our part, all the Proſpect that is before us, is onely ſuch an Univerſal Ruine, or ſuch a Government, as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Wiſdom of the Serpent, nor the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of Doves will enable us to eſcape the ill effects of.</p>
            <p>With ſome the Publick Safety is no motive to do their Duty, nor Common Calamities any
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63738:11"/>check to their Headſtrong Follies. But as thoſe that are thus hardned againſt ſuch Reproaches, ſeem to beſpeak for themſelves ſuch Calamities as belong to thoſe that upbraid the Care of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and have forfeited their Share in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Providence, ſo how well ſoever others may ſhift in the Hurries of the World, they have all Reaſon imaginable to expect to be made Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary in their Sufferings, if Heaven have any Hand in the Chances that attend Mortals. And thô the Reward of ſuch ſhould be reſerved by the Divine Counſel for another World, yet it muſt be owned that ſuch bid as fair every way for preſent Ruine, as one that ſtaves the Ship he ſails in, on purpoſe to get a Plank to ſave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from being ſwallowed up in the Raging O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean: So that as ſuch People ſeem to have out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lived all manner of Concern or Regard for the Publick; ſo likewiſe, to fall far ſhort of the Common Policy of Men, how Great States men ſoever they may be in their own Opinion: For certainly there is no ſuch way either for Perſonal, or the Publick Safety, as to be Juſt and True to the Government we live under, and, as God and Nature direct, to unite our Intereſts with it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The obſervance of this Rule in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to Almighty God, ſeems alſo to be, as of much Greater Moment, ſo alſo of as good Effect to this end; in as much both Kingdoms and Men have a greater dependance upon Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, than upon any thing elſe, and God hath a Greater Power over both, than all the World
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63738:11"/>hath; whether we ſee it or no, <hi>we live and move and have our beings in him?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act; 17.28.</note> And thô we think we may provide well enough for our ſelves by our own Induſtry and Management, yet we muſt be convinced, that God is the Great Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſer of our Fortunes here, as well as the Sole Arbiter of our Fate hereafter; and that he will not let go the Government of his own World, out of his own Hand. That Almighty God is unconcerned about the Affairs of the World, and takes no Notice of the Unrighteouſneſs and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts that are offered to him, is indeed what the vain Politicks of ſome Great States-men would perſwade, and that which the Wiſhes of ſome prompt them to believe and hope, but continual Experience, and that Senſe that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hath Planted in Humane Souls to prevent ſuch Dangerous Illuſions, convinceth us of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. And thoſe that are not willing to credit God's Word ſo far, yet are forced to believe that Good Men are under the Care of a Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and Gracious Providence, and that howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver others may fare, yet even in the worſt of Times, thoſe that fear God, are the moſt ſecure, and in the Happieſt Condition: And ſo Great and Viſible is his Power that <hi>Elihu</hi> challenges the World to oppoſe him, either in his Deſigns of Kindneſs, or in the Effects of his Indignation; <hi>When he giveth quietneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 31.29.</note> 
               <hi>who then can make trouble? And when he hideth his face, who then can behold him, whether it be done againſt a Nation, or againſt a man onely:</hi> And becauſe his Power extends not onely to this World, but
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63738:12"/>alſo to the utmoſt reach of Eternity, that Man certainly conſults beſt for himſelf, that hath a juſt Regard to him, and moſt Faithfully and Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly obſerves his Duty: Doubtleſs <hi>the work of</hi> ſuch <hi>righteouſneſs is peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 32.17.</note> 
               <hi>and the fruit of it, quietneſs and aſſurance for ever.</hi> Let things fall how they will in the World, he that keeps in with him that is the Great Orderer of all things now, and that muſt determine our Fate at laſt, is in the moſt ſecure State; however he may fare at preſent,<note place="margin">Pſal. 7.37.</note> 
               <hi>Mark the upright man, and behold the juſt, and the end of that man is peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to conclude; our Chriſtian Rule hath a more general tendency and influence and is the moſt Rational Security of Nations and States; Government is the Support and the Protection of Heaven, the Safety of any People, and the Foundation of a laſting Proſperity is laid in both: To <hi>render</hi> therefore <hi>to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and to God the things that are Gods,</hi> is the moſt Wiſe Proviſion for the Publick Good; and no People are ſo Happy as thoſe that are united in their Duty to God and their Princes. But on the other ſide, to have no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to God, is to cut off the beſt Defence, and inrage the moſt Dreadfull Enemy; to be falſe to the Prince, is to Renounce the moſt Natural Eſtabliſhment; and to be Unjuſt to both, is Fatal without remedy.</p>
            <p>Having thus far inſiſted upon what our Lord ſeems to intend in the Text; The Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63738:12"/>I would make of all is, to aſſiſt his moſt Gracious Deſign; to promote the Glory of God, the Repoſe of the World, and the Happineſs of Men; And, if I might, alſo help to mend the Ill State of theſe Times, and lend my Hand to lay a ground for our own Peace.</p>
            <p>It is too manifeſt that we are in a very Ill Caſe, and that moſt apparently, through the neglect of what our Saviour here enjoyns: Through the great decay of Piety, we are ſunk into a very Ill Habit; The Diſpleaſure of Heaven ſeems to be upon us already, and we Languiſh under the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of Greater ſtill; and this Ill Habit is ſo far Irrecoverable, that nothing but the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration of the Power of Godlineſs can reſtore us; and yet that onely Remedy ſeems to us as unacceptable as the Diſeaſe. Through the want of a due and orderly Submiſſion and Faithfulneſs to the Powers that be, we are become <hi>a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom divided</hi> and falſe <hi>within it ſelf.</hi> Our ſins have almoſt Ruined us, and the prevailing Power of Sedition, which hath broken the <hi>Craſis</hi> of this Politick Body, now looks like a near Forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſome Diſmal Fate. Virtue and Morality are ſunk, and the Nation looks rather Barbarous than Chriſtian: Rebellion ſets up for True Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; and that Uniform Submiſſion to Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is the Stability of Kingdoms and States is loſt: and by this wretched jumble of Impiety and Faction, of Vice and Sedition, Conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion creeps upon us, and a viſible Ruine calls aloud to Reform theſe Reproachfull Diſorders, and to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63738:13"/>
               <hi>render to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and to God the things that are Gods.</hi> And therefore to that end I preſume to perſwade theſe two things, which our Lord ſo expreſly calls for in the Text, and a third which apparent Neceſſity ſeems to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire in Reference thereto,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That we become more Juſt to Heaven.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That we become more Juſt to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Government we live under.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That all that are concerned in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, be ſo Juſt to God and their Majeſties, as to take a due care that theſe things be done.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That we become more Juſt to Heaven; That is that we come to a through Reformation of the Impieties that are daily ſo univerſally com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by all ſorts of Men to the Great Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God. This is that indeed which hath ſo often and ſo long been talkt of and pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; But ſo little of it is yet intended or done, that the prophane Age now takes the Advantage, and perfectly ridicules it. But yet this is it that muſt be our Refuge at laſt. We muſt either ceaſe our Provocations, or elſe we ſhall Experience that our <hi>iniquities will be our ruine;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 12.25. Ezek. 18.30.</note> We muſt either come to a more Pious Temper, or elſe we muſt never expect the Bleſſing of God in this World, or Mercy in the next; neither Proſperity here, nor a Lot among the Saints at laſt. This hath always been the means that God himſelf hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded for the averting of his Judgements and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63738:13"/>attoning incenſed Vengeance; And thoſe that have been ſo Wiſe as to make uſe of it, have ever found it Succeſsfull; whilſt a continued ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in their Impieties hath never failed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh his wrath upon wicked and unreclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able People.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that have made the moſt Wiſe Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Hiſtory of common Calamities, and the Ruine of Empires and Nations, have commonly aſſigned the cauſe thereof to the vices and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, either of the People, or their Princes; whereby, as they have become too effeminate and ſoft to be either Valiant or Wiſe, ſo they have at once loſt their Courage and Conduct, and incenſed Divine Juſtice againſt them. And if we look into the Holy Scripture (which onely gives us an Impartial Account of ſuch things) we ſhall find that all the Deſolations that are there mentioned to have been in the World, were more owing to the vile Practices of Men, and their ſins againſt God, than to the Power of Enemies: Look upon the Deſtruction of the <hi>Old World,</hi> and <hi>the overthrow of</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morra,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.5, 6, 7. Gen. 18.20. &amp; Chap. 19.24, 25.</note> Adma <hi>and</hi> Zeboim, and you will find the true cauſe of all their Ruine was their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Enormities, and their Brutiſh Practiſes, and becauſe they would not be brought to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Reformation, thò <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>juſt Lot,</hi> as well as their own Deſtruction ſo earneſtly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded it. And S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> ſays,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>theſe things were an enſample for thoſe that ſhould after live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly;</hi> Look upon thoſe ſeven Nations that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63738:14"/>God gave over to be deſtroyed before the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael,<note place="margin">Levit. 18.25, 28.</note> and you will find, that <hi>becauſe they had polluted it with their abominations, the land it ſelf</hi> is ſaid to have <hi>vomited them out;</hi> And God chargeth his own People not to follow their Example, <hi>That the land ſpue not them out alſo, as it ſpued out the Nations that were before them.</hi> Look upon the final Deſolation of the Jewiſh State and Nation; and their continued Obſtinacy and Rebellions againſt God, notwithſtanding the repeated Calls of our Lord and his Apoſtles to Repentance, was their Ruine: Our Saviour had indeed before read them their Deſtiny under the Parable of <hi>the Husbandmen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 21.23, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>that would not render their Lord the fruit of his Vineyard.</hi> And they might well have taken the hint in our Text: For, not <hi>rendring to God the things that were Gods,</hi> they (to bring on their own Deſtruction) were ſo beſotted as not to <hi>render to Caeſar the things that were Caeſars;</hi> but mutining about the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man tribute,</hi> under <hi>Florus</hi> and <hi>Albinus,</hi> they loſt their Temple, Sacrifice, and Service; and after they had ſuffered the moſt Diſmal Shock of Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty that ever fell upon any part of Mankind, their State was utterly overthrown. The old <hi>Perſian Empire,</hi> when ſunk into Debauchery, and ſtewed into Softneſs and Effeminacy by their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable Luſts, eaſily fell before the ſmall Force of <hi>Alexander;</hi> and that which made him <hi>Great,</hi> was, that he happened to extend his Arms where Luxury and Vice had made way for Conqueſt and Deſtruction before: And nothing gives the preſent Scourge of <hi>Europe</hi> a clearer Proſpect of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63738:14"/>
               <hi>an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy,</hi> then the Univerſal Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs and Impiety, (his moſt agreeable Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bingers) that have prepared his way: And he is certainly as much beholden to the Perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Treachery, to the Knavery and Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoòd that Irreligion and the Decay of Piety have ſo plentifully produced in this Age, as he is to any thing elſe, except it be the Divine Vengeance, that is now Chaſtiſing this part of Chriſtendom, with that Firebrand, for our great degeneracy in Religion and Manners.</p>
            <p>Theſe things are certainly very plain Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions to us, <hi>upon whom the ends of the world are come,</hi> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks: And if ſuch warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and our own Ill State; neither the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God upon others, nor the Proſpect of them upon our ſelves; neither the preſent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of his Diſpleaſure, nor the terrours of the Wrath to come, will prevail with us to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider our ways, and to come to a more Pious Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and more Chriſtian Practice, he that runs may read our Fate: For what our Lord ſaid to the Jews, is as applicable to us, both as to Particulars and as to the Nation in general,<note place="margin">Luke 13.3.</note> 
               <hi>Except ye repent ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let not therefore Religion and Piety which are a better Defence than either Walls or Bulworks, and the onely means to ſave our Souls, be the onely contemned things in the World, and Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick and Buſineſs be preferred before both. Let not the Sacred Ordinances of God be treated as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63738:15"/>mere Diverſions, and leſs eſteemed than Masks or Plays: Let not his Holy Day be onely reſpected as a Retirement from Publick Employments, to more Private Indulgence and Licentiouſneſs, and the reſt eſteemed moſt uſefull to us: Let not the Holy Name of God be more uſed to Swear and Curſe with, than to Adore and Praiſe: Let not our Glorious Creator, and moſt Mercifull Lord, the Great Judge of Quick and Dead, and the Almighty Revenger, be treated as an Inſignificant Being, and left out of our thoughts: Let not his Laws be contemned, his Counſels ſlighted, his Mercy abuſed, or his Judgements be provoked: But let us all Unite in his Fear, and by a time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and through Reformation of ſuch Horrid Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, endeavour at once to prevent the pouring out of his Fury upon the Land, and the Final Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of our own Souls.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I am to perſwade a juſt rendring <hi>to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars:</hi> that we come to a more united adherence to <hi>the Powers that be,</hi> and to a more juſt Obſervance of thoſe Duties that Gods word and the Neceſſity of Affairs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires in reference to them. This is the moſt Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional and Natural Method to aſſiſt that means which God and Nature have ordained, both for the Eſtabliſhment and Defence of Humane Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and the Common-wealth; and next to the propitiating of Heaven, by our returning to our Duty to God, it is the moſt Proper Courſe to prevent and diſſipate our Dangers:<note place="margin">Matth. 12.25.</note> Our Lord hath given us too plain a hint of the Danger that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63738:15"/>States are in, to be either overlooked or contemned: and if we will not yet take warning, it is too probable, we ſhall find his words true. When the Subjects of this Kingdom were ſo cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied in their Faith, as to reſerve a kind of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to the Prince of the <hi>Roman</hi> State, as they could not be ſo firmly United to the Common Intereſt of their own Princes and Country, as was neceſſary to its Freedom and Safety; ſo if we tranſcribe the Errour, that we have ſo often Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, and they ſo Happily eſcaped, it is but to make a very forward ſtep to engulf our ſelves into the ſame Condition and Worſe. And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſuch a Proſpect is not ſo very inviting, but that the Dreadfull Confuſions and Miſeries that muſt uſher it in, and attend it, might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with Men, not to be ſo paſſionately in Love with it.</p>
            <p>It is no ſtanding to diſpute Titles, and to fall out about what God ſeems to have determined, when without a Vigorous concurrence with the way that his Providence hath put us into for our Safety, we are the moſt Unfortunate People in the World. If all that are concern'd (as even thoſe alſo ſeem to be as much as any others that are ſo willing to run the adventure of another Revolution) would but concur in the ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Intereſt; to partake of the Common Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, will certainly be a Greater Reward, than they can expect for aſſiſting the Ruine of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try by Treachery and Perfidiouſneſs: Enraged Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny ſeldom makes Diſtinctions, and General Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63738:16"/>doth not always leave room for the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors to eſcape, eſpecially if their Numbers are many, and their Figures great; ſo that their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is not like to be ſo much according to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, as deſert. But to wave all Fears, let us all lay aſide that Diſcord and Falſhood that are at once ſo great a Reproach, and ſuch Fatal forerunners of miſchief; Let us concert for the Publick Safety, and Unite in the ſame Intereſt; and by a Cheerfull and Honeſt rendring <hi>to Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar the things that are Caeſars,</hi> let us ſtrengthen the Hands of our Princes, which is now the onely way left for the Preſervation of the Church and State, of our Country and Religion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, But to conclude; The laſt thing I am to perſwade, is, that all that are concern'd in the Government, would take a due Care that theſe things be done, and that all Men <hi>render to Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar the things that are Caeſars, and to God the things that are Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is that Juſtice that all in Authority owe to God and their Princes; and the Faithfull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of that Duty, is to conſult Wiſely for their own Safety and Honour, as well as for the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and the Eſtabliſhment of that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment they ſerve. <hi>To execute judgement</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Man and Man, <hi>and do juſtice,</hi> is the Indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable and Indiſpenſable Command of God; and without it Societies cannot be preſerved, nor States and Empire long upheld. For Juſtice is the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the Affairs of the World,<note place="margin">Prov, 16.12.</note> and <hi>the throne
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63738:16"/>is eſtabliſhed by righteouſneſs.</hi> But to neglect the juſt Intereſts of Princes and the Glory of God, is to countermine the other Practice: For to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Affronts and Impieties that the Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and Prophane temper of the Age is ſo very Pregnant with, to go unpuniſhed, is to forfeit the Care of Heaven, and beſpeak all the Judgements of God: And to ſuffer thoſe Affronts to Princes and their Government which the perverſe Humours of turbulent Spirits are ſo ſubject to, is to give way to their fall: Whereas a Faithful Diſcharge of thoſe Grand Duties, would as much as may be prevent thoſe Dangers, and not onely ſo, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo would render ſuch Noble Patriots names Great, their Memory Honourable, and themſelves Bleſſed.</p>
            <p>It is no wonder to hear Men <hi>deſpiſe dominion</hi> and ſpeak evil of Dignities,<note place="margin">Jude 8.</note> if they may do it without a check; and it is no wonder if Men without controul Blaſpheme the Moſt High, to hear them <hi>revile the Gods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 22.28.</note> 
               <hi>and curſe the Rulers of their people;</hi> But if the Power of Religion and the true Spirit of Government be ſo ſunk that theſe Practices are common and unpuniſhed, it would be a Wonder indeed, if they do not Ruine the Government that ſhould ſuppreſs them, and bring Confuſion upon the Land.</p>
            <p>To obviate therefore the Power of theſe Black Arts, and in behalf of all that fear God and love their Country and Religion, I preſume in the Name of God to demand that Juſtice which is ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently his, and his Vicegerents due, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63738:17"/>the Common Welfare hath ſo Great depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance. And becauſe Magnanimity and Courage as well as Juſtice is requiſite in this Caſe, the Enemies of our Peace being ſo many and Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of both ſorts, let Almighty God, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and lover of Juſtice and the Faithfull Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder of Good Men, ſtrengthen your Hands and Hearts to this Good Work, and give Succeſs to your Endeavours.</p>
            <p>Thus have I endeavoured to aſſiſt the kind Deſign of our moſt Loving Friend and Saviour; And ſo far as it ſucceeds, there ſhall be <hi>Glory to God, Peace on Earth, and good will towards Men:</hi> Which the Lord of his Infinite Goodneſs grant in our days for Jeſus Chriſt's ſake, to whom onely with the Holy Ghoſt be Adoration and Glory for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:63738:17"/>
            <head>Books Printed for, and ſold by <hi>Samuel Oliver</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>DE Naturali Religione Liber, in tres partes divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: ubi falſa candidè refelluntur, vera probantur, vel deteguntur, ac Orthodox. Eccleſ. fratres ad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiam vocantur. Autore <hi>Petr. Chanvin. Roterodami</hi> apud <hi>Pet. Vander Staart,</hi> ſumptibus <hi>Sam. Oliverii Norvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſis.</hi> 1693.</p>
            <p>A Sermon preach'd at the Aſſizes at <hi>Thetford</hi> 1693. by <hi>J. R.</hi> A. M. Rector of <hi>Brundal</hi> in <hi>Norfolk.</hi> Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd at the Special inſtance and Command of the Judges.</p>
            <p>The Duty and Encouragement of Religious Artiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers deſcrib'd in a Sermon preach'd in the Cathedral Church of <hi>Norwich,</hi> at the <hi>Weavers</hi> Guild. 1693. By <hi>J. Jeffery,</hi> A. M. Miniſter of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> of <hi>Mancroft</hi> in <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
